Finding Aid for Leslie Corsa Papers 1937-1984
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Leslie Corsa papers 1937-1984
Corsa, Leslie, 1920-
6 linear feet
Population planning director of Center for Population Planning at the University of Michigan. Diaries, correspondence, research on population planning in China, faculty minutes and general files for Center and Department of Population Planning; also materials relating to the School of Public Health.
8750 Aa 2
Bentley Historical Library University of Michigan
The collection was the gift of Patricia Corsa (donor no. 7369 ) and came to the library in two accessions, September and October 1986.
The collection is open for research.
Leslie Corsa, Jr. was born in Brooklyn, New York, October 10, 1920. He earned a degree in chemical engineering from Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1941 and received his MD from Harvard Medical School in 1946. His internship was in Oakland, California where he met and married Patricia Phillips in 1948. In 1952, Corsa received his M.P.H. in preventative medicine and public health from Harvard's School of Public Health.
Returning to California, Corsa served as chief of the Bureau of Maternal and Child Health in the state's department of public health. here, Corsa was involved in epidemiological research relating to human reproduction and childhood accidents. During 1959-1960, Corsa also served as chairman of the Maternal and Child Health section of the American Public Health Association. In this capacity he introduced family planning to the government in Karachi, Pakistan.
In 1965, Corsa was asked by the University of Michigan to direct its newly established Center for Population Planning in the School of Public health. The success of this center under his leadership resulted in the formation in 1970 of a department of population planning. Corsa served as its first and only chairman.
In 1972, Corsa took a leave of absence to serve as consultant in population planning to the World Health Organization in Geneva. In 1977 he resigned as chairman of the Department of Population Planning to begin a study of birth planning in China. His book, written with Deborah Oakley, Population Planning was published in 1979. Then, for eighteen months he was a consultant to the US Congress in the Office of Technology Assessment. In 1981 he returned to rural China to do field research in birth planning.
Upon his retirement in December 1983, the University of Michigan School of Public Health named Leslie Corsa professor emeritus of population planning. He died of cancer March 2, 1984.
The Leslie Corsa, Jr. collection consists of six linear feet of papers covering the years 1937 to 1986. In addition to some biographical material, mainly articles about Corsa and personal notes that he entitled "The Course of My Life" in which he discusses his education and training in the period 1940-1947, the bulk of the collection consists of professional correspondence, personal diaries, and subject files relating almost entirely to his career and professional interest in population planning. These subject files largely reflect Corsa's organizational activities: Center for Population Planning (of the U-M's School of Public Health); Department of Population Planning; and School of Public Health. There is also a China series consisting of correspondence and other materials gathered by Corsa in his study of population planning in China. Much of this research was done jointly with Dr. Pi Chao Chen of Wayne State University. The collection concludes with a series of topical files, some of which concern his association with the American Public Health Association and the Office of Technology Assessment in 1979-1980.
Subjects:
China--History--1949-; Birth control.; Population policy.; University of Michigan. Center for Population Planning.; University of Michigan. Dept. of Population Planning.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan. School of Public Health.
Subjects - Visual Material:
Children.; Cooking utensils.; Corsa, Leslie, 1920-1984; Offices.
Genre/Form:
Diaries.; Photographs.
- Biographical Material
  - Miscellaneous (Box 1)
  - "The Course of My Life": personal notes 1940-1947 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - General
    - 1949-1955 (scattered) (Box 1)
    - 1965-1984, 12 folders (Box 1)
  - "End of the Year Letters," 1954-1984 (Box 1)
  - Beasley, Dr. Joseph D. (Box 1)
  - Geijerskam, K. Gunnar af 1963-1971 (Box 1)
  - Hai Teh, M. (Box 1)
  - Hoffman, Lois (Box 1)
  - Jessup, Bruce (Box 1)
  - Johnson, J. Timothy (Box 1)
  - Kar, Snehendu B. (Box 1)
  - Oakley, Deborah (Box 1)
  - Peng, J.Y.
    - 1965-1969 (Box 1)
    - 1972-1975 (Box 1)
    - 1976-1978 (Box 1)
  - Peterson, Bob (Box 1)
  - Preble, Beth (Box 1)
  - Remington, Richard, Dean, School of Public Health (Box 1)
  - Roderick, Larry S. (Box 1)
  - Rodrieguez, Aurora (Box 1)
  - Rockefeller, John D. III 1963 (Box 1)
  - Balfour, Marshall C., MD (Box 1)
  - Takeshita, Yuauru 1969-1978 (Box 1)
  - Wegman, Myron, Dean, School of Public Health (Box 1)
- Diaries
  - 1937 (Box 1)
  - 1938 (Box 1)
  - 1939 (Box 1)
  - 1940 (Box 1)
  - 1943 (Box 2)
  - 1944 (Box 2)
  - 1949 (Box 2)
  - 1950 (Box 2)
  - 1951 (Box 2)
  - 1955 (Box 2)
  - 1981 China (Box 2)
- Center for Population Planning
  - Faculty Meeting Minutes 1967-1970, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Governing Body Meetings 1970-1971 (Box 2)
  - Operating Committee Records 1965-1971 (Box 2)
  - Staff Meeting Minutes 1965-1969, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Executive Committee Minutes September 1970-December 1975, 3 folders (Box 2)
- Department of Population Planning
  - Faculty Meetings 1971-1976, 3 folders (Box 2)
  - Finances 1974-1977, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - General Files 1970-1976, 13 folders (Box 3)
  - Governing Body Minutes September 1973-July 1976, 3 folders (Box 3)
  - Grant papers [211(d)], 3 folders (Box 4)
  - Policy and Procedure Manual 1974 (Box 4)
  - Termination of Department 1978 (Box 4)
- China Materials
  - Birth planning in China 1978 (Box 4)
  - Chen, Pi-Chao, Political Science Professor, Wayne State
    - American Public Health Association 1978 (Box 4)
    - China 1979 (Box 4)
    - China Report 1979 (Box 4)
    - Correspondence 1977-1982 (Box 4)
    - Population Report 1981 (Box 4)
  - Chen-Corsa 1981 Proposal (Box 4)
  - China Conference, University of Michigan 1982 (Box 4)
  - China National Survey 1982 (Box 4)
  - Committee on Scholarly Communication with the People's Republic of China
    - General 1981 (Box 4)
    - Application November 1983 (Box 4)
    - Briefing materials November 1980 (Box 4)
    - Miscellaneous 1983 (Box 4)
  - Health and Human Services, US Department of 1981 (Box 4)
  - Huaide County, maps and report 1980 (Box 4)
  - International Planned Parenthood Federation, China Trips 1977-1978 (Box 4)
  - Jida Seminar undated (Box 4)
  - Jilin University, correspondence 1980-1982 (Box 4)
  - Lyle, Kathyrn Chiu 1979 (Box 4)
  - Michigan Conference PW/People's Republic of China May 1972 (Box 4)
  - Preliminary Report 1981 (Box 4)
  - Population Planning Seminar 1974 (Box 4)
  - Ravenholt, R.T., China article (Box 4)
  - Rogers, Everett, two reports on health and birth planning in China 1978 (Box 4)
  - State Department 1980 (Box 4)
  - United Nations Fund for Population Activities, correspondence 1980-1982 (Box 5)
  - US-China Peoples Friends Association
    - Chronicle of medical group 1978 (Box 5)
    - China trip, miscellaneous 1978 (Box 5)
    - Report 1978 (Box 5)
    - Trip 1978 (Box 5)
  - United States Embassy, Peking 1979 (Box 5)
  - Wegman, Myron E., "Visit to People's Republic of China" (Box 5)
  - Winfield China paper (Box 5)
- School of Public Health
  - Advisory Council Minutes 1972-1974 (Box 5)
  - Development Committee Meetings 1971-1972 (Box 5)
  - Executive Committee Minutes 1974-1979, 6 folders (Box 5)
  - Faculty Minutes 1965-1974, 9 folders (Box 5)
  - General Files 1977, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - Policies, 2 folders (Box 6)
  - University Services Agreement, Grant AID/Csd-3321, 5 folders (Box 6)
  - Venezuela 1975 (Box 6)
- Topical Files
  - American Public Health Association
    - Memos 1971-1978 (scattered) (Box 6)
    - Minutes and miscellaneous 1981-1982 (Box 6)
    - Population Section Council
      - Minutes 1976-1981 (Box 6)
      - Recommendations, Resolutions, Charges to task force 1971 (Box 6)
  - House Select Committee on Population, Congressman James H. Scheuer 1978 (Box 6)
  - Office of Technology Assessment
    - Global energy 1979 (Box 6)
    - Project proposals 1979 (Box 6)
    - Related Assessments outside 1979 (Box 6)
    - Reports 1980 (Box 6)
    - Staff Memos, March and April, 1980 (Box 6)
    - UNICEF 1980 (Box 6)
  - Population Club
    - Chronological record of meetings 1965-1975, 2 folders (Box 6)
    - General 1972 (Box 6)
  - Photographs (Box 6)
    Portraits, and photos of meetings; candid photos of Corsa as a child, in the office, at home, and on various travels abroad.
  - Publications (Box 6)